another thing i want to talk about today
is what is a buy-back
option what do we mean if we give you a
buy-back
option on your insurance um so a life
insurance buy-back option is usually
available to policies that are
bundled with either tpd trauma or trauma
insurance now if you want to have a look
i've got another slide presentation that
i have done on what i mean by
linked or bundled and standalone this is
a really common structure
for in life insurance policies as it
does lower the cost of having separate
insurances and it does mean however
if you do make a trauma or tpd claim
your life insurance
benefit is reduced by the amount of that
claim so this is why insurance
companies do offer a buy back option
if you want it so how does the buyback
option work
a buy-back option is added to your
policy and let's just say you have 500
in life insurance cover and 300 000 in
tpd insurance and you make a claim under
your tpd
after the claim your life insurance will
be reduced to just
two hundred thousand because you've
already claimed three hundred thousand
to reflect basically the claim that
you've already made but you fit
in within your policy you may be able to
buy back
the tpd insurance at a later date this
means that after 12 months you can
reinstate your life insurance back up to
the original 500 000 of cover
and in essence buying back to your
original cover amount
so what kind of um about buyback options
are available so you've got tpd buyback
so basically a tpb tpd buyback is a
standard buyback option that allows you
to reinstate the full amount of your
insurance policies 12
to 12 months after you've made a tpd
claim
um you've got trauma buyback so trauma
buyback works the same way as the tpd
um but is for trauma such as your heart
attack obviously illness
a trauma reinstatement um is an
additional
option that allows you to have multiple
claims to be made against the same
single trauma policy um so if you have
claimed your problem uh claimed
everything
on trauma you um have your policy
you've actually exhausted your policy so
to speak um you can actually have a
reinstatement that gives you the option
of making
um further claims as if there was
another situation otherwise you may need
um another policy so what should you be
um considering when you're looking at a
buy-back
option why should you consider
it it does provide a bit of a safety net
for your family in case of illness and
death and if you don't have a buy-back
option the cover will be to reduce the
amount and it may not be suitable to
your family needs but again
it also comes down to the cost of it as
well i know
so how does it come in handy consider a
scenario where
um someone suffers a heart attack is
unable to work the trauma insurance will
cover the
costs of the with the heart attack but
this will be deducted from the life
insurance
amount a buy-back is important because
after 12 months the life insurance
can be re instated to the full amount of
the life insurance claim
is will be paid in full um if there was
to be an incident and it's usually done
without
further underwriting um required if that
um
if that is needed um and there is
um is there an additional cost um yes
usually there is an additional cost on
this
um sometimes uh other insurers use
buyback as an
option to be bundled and therefore um
you know it can be
an additional cost some may have it
included
a standalone option um not bundled with
insurances
um not bundled um the buyback option
will generally cost a lot more however
there is flexibility so
as a bundled option the buyback policy
will definitely
potentially be included in the overall
insurance premium
so it really comes down to the
structuring when we're putting that to
um
together so what are the some um what
are some of the condition
the conditions when we actually go
through that come with a buyback
option some insurers will require
underwriting and new premiums
um it may have an expiration date based
off the age
um it may be a partial buyback or a full
depending on the terms that you've
agreed
and a repurchase term insurance may not
be eligible for indexation so
that um it depends on the situation a
buyback may be dependent on health
habits
um and it also may be based off a 12
month or
one year which can affect the repayment
date so
um there are some different factors that
are considered but it definitely is an
option depending on your personal
circumstances so that is something we
can discuss with you
um if you've got any questions please
don't hesitate to contact us
thank you